Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 43: Hemorrhagic Placental Disorders.
Placental Abruption Diagnosis Management Placenta Previa Diagnosis Management Placenta Accreta Spectrum Diagnosis Management References Hemorrhage following partial or complete separation of the placenta can be torrential.
Recall that the amount of blood flowing through the intervillous space at term exceeds 600 mL/min .
In the second half of pregnancy, three placental disorders contribute substantially to maternal mortality rates.
These include placental abruption, placenta previa, and placenta accreta spectrum.
The contributions of hemorrhagic placental disorders to maternal mortality are discussed in Chapter 1 (p. 7) and Chapter 42 (p. 733).
The management and clinical experience with these disorders span more than a generation.
Placental abruption, for example, has been emphasized in this text for more than 50 years beginning with the work of Dr. Jack Pritchard.
Now more common than years past, placenta accreta spectrum is another substantial threat to maternal well-being.
Placental Abruption.
# Etiopathogenesis.
Separation of the placenta—either partially or totally—from its implantation site before delivery is called placental abruption or abruptio placentae.
From Latin, the latter translates as “rending asunder of the placenta,” which denotes a sudden accident, which is characteristic of most cases.
In the purest sense, the cumbersome—and thus seldom used—term premature separation of the normally implanted placenta is most descriptive because it excludes separation of a placenta previa.
Abruption likely begins with rupture of a decidual spiral artery and hemorrhage into the decidual basalis.
The subsequent expanding retroplacental hematoma splits the decidua and leaves a thin layer adherent to the myometrium.
The decidual hematoma grows to lift away and compress the adjacent placenta.
In some cases that are associated with preeclampsia, impaired trophoblastic invasion with subsequent atherosis is one underlying predisposition .
Inflammation or infection also may be contributory .
However, histological findings cannot be used to determine the timing of the abruption .
In the early stages of placental abruption, clinical symptoms may be absent.
Even with continued bleeding and placental separation, placental abruption can still be either total or partial .
With either, bleeding typically insinuates itself between the membranes and uterine wall, ultimately escaping through the cervix to cause external hemorrhage.
Less often, the blood is retained, leading to concealed hemorrhage and delayed diagnosis.
The delay translates into greater maternal and fetal hazards.
With concealed hemorrhage, the likelihood of consumptive coagulopathy is also increased.
This is because increased pressure within the intervillous space, caused by the expanding retroplacental clot, forces more placental thromboplastin into the maternal circulation .
Figure 43-1.
Schematic of placental abruption.
Shown to the left is total placental abruption with concealed hemorrhage.
To the right is a partial abruption with blood and clots that dissect between membranes and decidua to reach the internal cervical os and then the vagina.
Most blood in the retroplacental hematoma in a nontraumatic placental abruption is maternal.
This is because hemorrhage derives from separation within the maternal decidua, and placental villi are usually initially intact.
In 78 women at Parkland Hospital with a nontraumatic placental abruption, fetal-to-maternal hemorrhage was documented in only 20 percent.
All of these had <10 mL fetal blood loss .
In another series of 68 women with a placental abruption, fetal cells were found in peripheral blood in only 4 percent .
Placental abruption can create a visible circumscribed depression on the maternal surface of a freshly delivered placenta.
These depressions usually measure a few centimeters in diameter and are covered by dark, clotted blood.
Because several minutes are required for these anatomical changes to materialize, a very recently
separated placenta may appear totally normal at delivery.
Our experiences are like those of Benirschke and associates (2012) in that the “age” of the retroplacental clot cannot be determined exactly.
In the example shown in Figure 43-2, a large dark clot is well formed.
It has depressed the placental bulk and likely is at least several hours old.
Figure 43-2.
Partial placental abruption with a dark adherent clot.
Defining placental abruption severity is problematic.
We consider placental abruption severe when the fetus dies.
However, maternal and fetal complications are frequently serious even with a liveborn fetus.
Ananth and coworkers (2016) have defined severe placental abruption as displaying one or more of the following: (1) maternal sequelae that include disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), shock, transfusion, hysterectomy, renal failure, or death; (2) fetal complications such as nonreassuring fetal status, growth restriction, or death; or (3) neonatal outcomes that include death, preterm delivery, or growth restriction.
Traumatic Abruption External trauma—usually from motor vehicle crashes or aggravated assault —can cause placental separation.
The frequency of abruption originating from trauma varies.
Importantly, abruption can stem from relatively minor trauma .
The clinical presentation and consequences of these abruptions differ somewhat from spontaneous cases.
For example, associated fetomaternal hemorrhage, while seldom clinically significant with most spontaneous abruptions, is more common with trauma because of concomitant placental tears or “fractures” (Fig. 50-10, p. 895).
In eight women with traumatic placental abruption cared for at Parkland Hospital, we found fetal-to-maternal hemorrhage of 80 to 100 mL in three .
Importantly, in some cases of trauma, a nonreassuring fetal heart rate tracing may not be accompanied by other evidence of placental separation.
A sinusoidal tracing is one example.
Following blunt abdominal trauma, uterine contractions are the single most important predictor of placental abruption .
Traumatic abruption is considered in more detail in Chapter 50 (p. 894).
Chronic Abruption When placental separation is not followed by delivery, the placental abruption is termed chronic.
Some of these cases begin early in pregnancy.
Dugoff and coworkers (2004) observed an association between some abnormally elevated maternal serum aneuploidy markers and subsequent abruption.
Others have correlated first- and second-trimester bleeding with third-trimester placental abruption (Ananth, 2006; Weiss, 2004).
In some cases, chronic abruption and oligohydramnios develop and are called the chronic abruption–oligohydramnios sequence (CAOS) .
Even later in pregnancy, hemorrhage with retroplacental hematoma formation is occasionally arrested completely without delivery.
These women may have abnormally elevated levels of maternal serum alpha-fetoprotein (MSAFP) or placenta-specific RNAs as markers of the event (Miura, 2017; Ngai, 2012).
# Frequency.
The reported incidence of placental abruption varies because of differing criteria used for diagnosis.
Its frequency averages 0.5 percent or 1 case in 200 deliveries.
From one database of more than 125 million births from 1979 through 2010, the incidence of placental abruption was nearly 1 percent .
In more than 250,000 deliveries at Parkland Hospital from 2000 through 2015, the incidence of placental abruption averaged 1 case in 290 births .
Figure 43-3.
Frequency of placental abruption and placenta previa by maternal age at Parkland Hospital from 2000 through 2015.
The frequency of placental abruption has risen in this country, and most of this increase is in black women (Ananth, 2005, 2016).
This disproportion may be explained in part by the conservative management of early-onset preeclampsia in some institutions .
At Parkland Hospital, however, the frequency of severe placental abruption has declined.
Specifically, with placental abruption so extensive as to kill the fetus, the incidence was 0.24 percent or 1 case in 420 births from
1956 through 1967 .
Through 2020, this same frequency dropped to 0.05 percent or 1 case in 2060 births.
This likely reflects a concurrent decline in the number of high-parity women giving birth and rise in the availability of prenatal care and emergency transportation.
# Perinatal Morbidity and Mortality.
Overall, perinatal outcomes are influenced by gestational age, and the frequency of placental abruption rises across the third trimester.
As seen in Figure 43-4.
more than half of the placental abruptions at Parkland Hospital developed at gestational ages ≥37 weeks’ gestation.
Perinatal mortality and morbidity, however, are more common with earlier abruptions and with concomitant preeclampsia (Furukawa, 2015; Han, 2019).
Of other related factors, major fetal congenital anomalies have greater association with placental abruption (Riihimäki, 2013).
Figure 43-4.
Frequency of placental abruption by gestational age at Parkland Hospital.
Although the rates of fetal death have declined, the contribution of abruption as a cause of stillbirth remains prominent because other causes also have decreased.
For example, since the early 1990s, 10 to 12 percent of all third-trimester stillbirths at Parkland Hospital have been the consequence of placental abruption.
In a review of more than 15 million singleton births between 1995 and 1998 in the United States, the perinatal mortality rate associated with placental abruption was 119 death per 1000 births.
This was higher than the rate of 8 deaths per 1000 births in the general obstetrical population .
Neonatal deaths also are common following placental abruption.
At Parkland Hospital, 15 percent of liveborn neonates die.
Perinatal morbidity also is common in this group .
Moreover, associated childhood mortality mainly stems from birth-related asphyxia and prematurity (Riihimäki, 2018).
In one series, 20 percent of 43 liveborn neonates had severe fetal acidemia following placental abruption, and 20 percent of survivors developed cerebral palsy .
In another study of 84 liveborns, 29 (35 percent) had an umbilical artery pH <7.00 .
Ananth and coworkers (2017) attribute some of the adverse neurodevelopmental outcomes to preterm delivery.
# Predisposing Factors.
Demographic Factors Several predisposing factors raise the placental abruption risk .
Advancing maternal age is one risk, although data regarding women of great parity are conflicting (see Fig. 43-3) .
Race or ethnicity also appears important .
In an earlier study, in almost 366,000 deliveries at Parkland Hospital, abruption severe enough to kill the fetus was most common in black and white women—1 case in 200 births; less so in Asian women—1 in 300; and least common in Latinas—1 in 350 .
A familial association was found from one Norwegian populationbased registry .
In this study, if a woman had a severe abruption, the risk for her sister was doubled.
Candidate genes involved in mitochondrial biogenesis and oxidative phosphorylation pathways, which confer risk for placental abruption, have been described .
Table 43-1.
Risk Factors for Placental Abruption Pregnancy-associated Hypertension Some form of hypertension is the most frequent condition associated with placental abruption.
This includes gestational hypertension, preeclampsia, chronic hypertension, or a combination.
The hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme levels, low platelet count (HELLP) syndrome carries an increased risk for placental abruption.
Moreover, expectant management of preeclampsia in significantly preterm pregnancies was complicated by placental abruption in 4 percent .
In a report by Pritchard and colleagues (1991) that described 408 women with placental abruption and fetal demise, hypertension was apparent in half once hypovolemia was corrected.
Half of these latter women—a fourth of all 408—had chronic hypertension.
Examined another way, one Maternal-Fetal Medicine Units (MFMU) Network study found that 1.5 percent of pregnant women with chronic hypertension suffered placental abruption .
At Parkland Hospital, the placental abruption frequency
in women with treated chronic hypertension and significant proteinuria was almost 1 percent.
This incidence compared with the 0.3-percent incidence in women with treated hypertension without substantial proteinuria .
Chronic hypertension with superimposed preeclampsia or with fetalgrowth restriction confers an even greater risk .
Even so, the severity of hypertension does not necessarily correlate with abruption incidence (Morgan, 2016; Zetterstrom, 2005).
However, women with preeclampsia that experience placental abruption have worse maternal, fetal, and neonatal outcomes compared with women experiencing abruption alone .
The long-term effects of these associations are apparent from the significantly elevated cardiovascular mortality risk in women with prior abruption, with or without chronic hypertension (DeRoo, 2016; Pariente, 2013).
Observations from the Magpie Trial Collaborative Group suggest that women with preeclampsia, with or without chronic hypertension, given magnesium sulfate may have a reduced risk for abruption .
Last, Roberge and colleagues (2018), performed a metaanalysis and reported that a 100-mg daily aspirin may decrease the incidence of placental abruption.
Preterm Prelabor Ruptured Membranes The placental abruption risk substantially rises when placental membranes rupture before term.
Of 756 women with ruptured membranes between 20 and 36 weeks’ gestation, 5 percent developed an abruption .
The frequency was 17 percent with previable prelabor ruptured membranes .
The risk for abruption with preterm membrane rupture is further elevated with comorbid infection .
In one cohort study of pregnancies ≥34 weeks’ gestation, the placental abruption rate was eightfold higher if hydramnios was comorbid .
From a metaanalysis of 10 studies that included term and preterm gestational ages, hydramnios was associated with a twofold greater rate of placental abruption .
Abrupt uterine decompression during membrane rupture may be an inciting factor.
Prior Abruption Many of the predisposing factors in women with a history of an abruption are chronic conditions, and in these cases, placental abruption has a high recurrence rate.
Women with abruption and fetal death have a recurrence rate of 12 percent, and half of these abruptions caused another fetal death .
Furuhashi and colleagues (2002) reported a 22-percent recurrence rate, and half recurred at a gestational age 1 to 3 weeks earlier than the first abruption.
In one longitudinal Dutch study, Ruiter and coworkers (2015) cited a recurrence risk of 5.8 percent.
In a populationbased study of 767,000 pregnancies, the authors found a sevenfold higher risk for recurrence of a “mild” abruption and twelvefold risk for a “severe” abruption .
For women who had two severe abruptions, the risk for a third was increased 50-fold.
Management of a pregnancy subsequent to an abruption is difficult because another separation may suddenly occur, even remote from term.
In many of these recurrences, evaluation of fetal well-being is almost always reassuring beforehand.
Thus, antepartum fetal testing is usually not predictive.
Because term abruptions tend to be recurrent, Ruiter and coworkers (2015) recommend labor induction at 37 weeks’ gestation.
It seems reasonable to induce labor at 38 completed weeks if other complications do not develop beforehand.
Other Associations Of these listed in Table 43-1, cigarette smoking is linked to an elevated risk for placental abruption .
One metaanalysis of 1.6 million pregnancies in smokers found a twofold risk .
This risk was five- to eightfold if smokers had chronic hypertension, severe preeclampsia, or both.
Similar findings are reported by others (Hogberg, 2007; Kaminsky, 2007).
Cocaine abuse is linked, and in one series of 50 women who abused cocaine during pregnancy, eight had a stillbirth caused by placental abruption .
Of potential serum markers, MSAFP, inhibin, and pregnancy-associated plasma protein in abnormal levels carry increased risk .
Indeed, preliminary data shows that MSAFP levels >280 µg/L in the third
trimester may be predictive .
Subclinical hypothyroidism or high levels of antithyroid antibodies have been associated with a two- to threefold higher risk for placental abruption (Abbassi-Ghanavati, 2010; Maraka, 2016).
Lupus anticoagulant is associated with maternal floor infarction of the placenta but is less so with typical abruptions.
Women affected by some of the thrombophilias have higher associated rates of thromboembolic events during pregnancy, however, no convincing evidence supports a link between thrombophilias and placental abruption (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019; 2020).
# Diagnosis.
The signs and symptoms of placental abruption can vary considerably.
Classically, affected women have a sudden onset of abdominal pain, vaginal bleeding, and uterine tenderness.
In an earlier study, 78 percent had vaginal bleeding, 66 percent had uterine tenderness or back pain, and 60 percent had a nonreassuring fetal status .
Other findings included frequent contractions and persistent hypertonus.
However, in a fifth, preterm labor was diagnosed, and placental abruption was not suspected until fetal distress or death followed.
In some women, external bleeding can be profuse, yet placental separation may not be so extensive as to compromise the fetus.
In others, external bleeding is absent, but the placenta is sufficiently sheared off to kill the fetus—a concealed abruption.
In either case, bleeding can be massive and leads to hypovolemic shock.
In an earlier report from Parkland Hospital, Pritchard and Brekken (1967) described 141 women with abruption so severe as to kill the fetus.
Blood loss in these women often amounted to at least half of their pregnant blood volume.
Consumptive Coagulopathy With placental abruption, some degree of intravascular coagulation is almost universal.
Placental abruption is the most common cause of clinically profound consumptive coagulopathy in obstetrics and probably in all specialties .
A primary consequence of intravascular coagulation is the activation of plasminogen to plasmin, which then lyses fibrin microemboli to maintain microcirculatory patency.
With placental abruption severe enough to kill the fetus, pathological levels of fibrinogen– fibrin degradation products and D-dimers are almost always found in maternal serum .
Their quantification is not clinically useful.
In a third of women with an abruption severe enough to kill the fetus, the plasma fibrinogen level will be <150 mg/dL.
These levels are dependent on the maternal preabruption fibrinogen level, and thus higher levels are “protective” (Cunningham, 2015; Wang, 2016).
Clinically significant low levels may cause troublesome surgical bleeding, and measurement of levels assists fibrinogen-replacement efforts.
Levels of several other coagulation factors also are variably decreased.
These are not specifically measured in DIC, but factors are replaced empirically with fresh frozen plasma as a part of massive transfusion protocols .
In addition, thrombocytopenia, sometimes profound, may accompany severe hypofibrinogenemia and can be common after repeated blood transfusions.
This “dilutional coagulopathy” is additive to DIC .
Consumptive coagulopathy is more likely with a concealed abruption because intrauterine pressure is higher.
This forces more thromboplastin into the large veins draining the implantation site.
With a partial abruption and a live fetus, severe coagulation defects are less common.
Our experience has been that if serious coagulopathy develops, it is usually evident by the time abruption symptoms appear.
In one unusual case, a woman cared for at Parkland Hospital presented with a nosebleed.
She had no pain or vaginal bleeding, but her fetus was dead.
Her blood did not clot, and the plasma fibrinogen level was 25 mg/dL.
A total placental abruption was confirmed at delivery.
Couvelaire Uterus At the time of cesarean delivery, it is not uncommon to find widespread extravasation of blood into the uterine musculature and beneath the serosa .
This phenomenon is named after
Couvelaire, who in the early 1900s termed it uteroplacental apoplexy.
These myometrial hemorrhages may incite uterine atony, but are not a sole indication for hysterectomy.
Effusions of blood may collect beneath the tubal serosa, between the leaves of the broad ligaments, in the ovaries, or in the peritoneal cavity.
Figure 43-5.
Couvelaire uterus from total placental abruption after cesarean delivery.
Blood markedly infiltrates the myometrium to reach the serosa.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Steven Blaine Holloway.
End-organ Injury Acute kidney injury (AKI) is a general term describing renal dysfunction from many causes .
Delayed or incomplete treatment of hypovolemia is one.
However, even with placental abruption complicated by severe DIC, prompt and vigorous treatment with blood and crystalloid solutions usually prevents significant renal dysfunction.
The risk for renal injury with placental abruption rises when preeclampsia coexists (Alexander, 2015; Drakeley, 2002).
Most cases of AKI are reversible, do not require dialysis, and generally have good long-term outcomes .
However, irreversible acute cortical necrosis occasionally stems from placental abruption .
Rarely, pituitary failure—Sheehan syndrome—follows severe intrapartum or early postpartum hemorrhage.
Described in Chapter 61 (p. 1104), the exact pathogenesis is not well understood, especially because endocrine abnormalities are infrequent even in women who suffer catastrophic hemorrhage .
Differential Diagnosis Severe placental abruption usually is obvious.
However, less severe forms are not always recognized with certainty, and the diagnosis becomes one of exclusion.
Unfortunately, no laboratory tests or other diagnostic methods accurately confirm lesser degrees of placental separation.
Sonography has limited use because the placenta and fresh clots may have similar imaging characteristics.
In a study of 149 women with a suspected placental abruption, the sensitivity for sonography was only 24 percent .
Thus, negative findings with sonographic examination do not exclude placental abruption.
Conversely, magnetic resonance (MR) imaging is highly sensitive for placental abruption and should be considered if the diagnostic information would change management .
Last, elevated serum levels of D-dimers may be suggestive, but this has not been adequately tested.
Thus, in the woman with vaginal bleeding and a live fetus, placenta previa and other bleeding causes are sought with clinical and sonographic evaluation.
It has long been taught—perhaps with some justification—that painful uterine bleeding signifies placental abruption, whereas painless uterine bleeding indicates placenta previa.
The differential diagnosis is usually not this straightforward, and labor accompanying previa may cause pain that suggests placental abruption.
Conversely, pain from placental abruption may mimic normal labor, or it may be painless, especially with a posterior placenta.
At times, the vaginal bleeding source remains obscure even after delivery.
# Management.
Treatment varies depending on maternofetal clinical condition, gestational age, and amount of associated hemorrhage.
With a living viable-aged fetus and with vaginal delivery not imminent, emergency cesarean delivery is chosen by most.
In some women, fetal compromise will be evident as shown in Figure 43-6.
When evaluating fetal status, sonographic confirmation of fetal heart activity may be necessary because sometimes an electrode applied directly to a dead fetus will provide misleading information by recording the maternal heart rate .
Figure 43-6.
Placental abruption with fetal compromise.
Lower panel: Uterine hypertonus with a baseline pressure of 20 to 25 mm Hg and frequent contractions peaking at approximately 75 mm Hg. Upper panel: The fetal heart rate demonstrates baseline bradycardia with repetitive late decelerations.
If the fetus has died or if it is not considered sufficiently mature to live outside the uterus, vaginal birth is preferable for the mother.
In either case, prompt and intensive
resuscitation with blood products and crystalloids is begun.
These measures are lifesaving for the mother and hopefully for her fetus.
If the diagnosis of placental abruption is uncertain and the fetus is alive and without evidence of compromise, close observation may be warranted provided that immediate intervention is available.
Colón and coworkers (2016) performed a randomized trial and found no benefits to magnesium sulfate tocolysis given to women with a preterm “nonsevere” abruption at 24 to 34 weeks’ gestation.
Cesarean Delivery The compromised fetus is usually best served by cesarean delivery, and the speed of response is an important factor in perinatal outcomes.
In one study of 33 singleton pregnancies with a clinically overt placental abruption and fetal bradycardia, 15 of the 22 neurologically intact survivors were delivered within a 20-minute decision-to-delivery interval .
However, eight of 11 infants who died or developed cerebral palsy were delivered after a 20-minute intervals.
Onishi and colleagues (2019) also found a significant negative correlation between these intervals and cord arterial pH.
At Parkland Hospital, placental abruption was one of the most powerful antecedents to body-cooling treatment for neonatal encephalopathy .
A major hazard to cesarean delivery is imposed by clinically significant consumptive coagulopathy.
Preparations include two large-bore intravenous catheters and plans for blood and component replacement.
Measures of hemoglobin, platelet, and fibrinogen levels as well as protime (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) guide product replacement.
Vaginal Delivery If the fetus has died, vaginal delivery is usually preferred.
As reviewed earlier, hemostasis at the placental implantation site depends primarily on myometrial contraction and not blood coagulability.
Thus, after vaginal delivery, uterotonic agents and uterine massage are used to stimulate myometrial contractions.
Uterine muscle fibers compress placental site vessels and prompt hemostasis even if coagulation is defective.
In some instances, vaginal delivery may not be preferable, even with a dead fetus.
One example is brisk hemorrhage that cannot be successfully managed by vigorous blood replacement.
Others are the myriad obstetrical complications that prohibit vaginal delivery in general.
In some women with extensive placental abruption, labor tends to be rapid because the uterus is usually persistently hypertonic (see Fig. 43-6).
This can magnify fetal compromise.
In some cases, baseline intraamnionic pressures reach 50 mm Hg or higher, and with contractions, pressures may attain levels exceeding 100 mm Hg. Overall, however, first- and second-stage labor does not appear to be shorter than usual .
Early amniotomy has long been championed in the management of placental abruption.
This ostensibly achieves better spiral artery compression to diminish implantation site bleeding and reduce thromboplastin infusion into the maternal vascular system.
Although evidence supporting this theory is lacking, membrane rupture may hasten delivery.
However, if the fetus is small, the intact sac may be more efficient in promoting cervical dilation.
If rhythmic uterine contractions are not superimposed on baseline hypertonus, oxytocin is given in standard doses.
No data indicate that oxytocin augments thromboplastin escape into the maternal circulation to worsen coagulopathy.
In 1ight of hypertonus associated with placental abruption, misoprostol may be a less favored induction agent due to its association with uterine tachysystole.
In the past, some had set arbitrary time limits to permit vaginal delivery.
Instead, experiences illustrate that maternal outcome depends on the diligence with which adequate fluid and blood replacement therapy are pursued rather than on the interval to delivery.
Observations from Parkland Hospital described by Pritchard and Brekken (1967) are similar to those from the University of Virginia reported by Brame and associates (1968).
Specifically, women with severe abruption who were transfused
during 18 hours or more before delivery had similar outcomes to those in whom delivery was accomplished sooner.
Expectant Management If possible, delaying delivery may benefit an immature fetus.
In one series, 43 women with placental abruption before 35 weeks’ gestation were expectantly managed, and 31 of them were given tocolytic therapy .
The mean interval until delivery for all 43 approximated 12 days.
Cesarean delivery was performed in 75 percent, and there were no stillbirths.
As discussed earlier, women with a very early abruption may develop chronic abruption–oligohydramnios sequence.
In one report, four women with an abruption at a mean gestational age of 20 weeks subsequently developed oligohydramnios and delivered at an average gestational age of 28 weeks .
In another description of 256 women with an abruption at <28 weeks’ gestation, a mean of 1.6 weeks was gained .
Of the group, 65 percent were delivered before 29 weeks, and half of all women underwent emergent cesarean delivery.
Unfortunately, even continuous fetal heart rate monitoring does not guarantee universally good outcomes.
A normal tracing may precede sudden further separation with instant fetal compromise.
In some of these, if the separation is sufficient, the fetus will die before it can be delivered.
Tocolysis is advocated by some for suspected abruption if the fetus does not display compromise.
Some investigators have observed that tocolysis improved outcomes in a highly selected cohort of women with preterm pregnancies (Bond, 1989; Combs, 1992).
In another study, Towers and coworkers (1999) administered magnesium sulfate, terbutaline, or both to 95 of 131 women with abruption diagnosed before 36 weeks’ gestation.
The perinatal mortality rate was 5 percent in both groups with or without tocolysis.
Similar results were reported from a randomized trial (Colón, 2016).
A clinical consideration to the use of tocolytic agents, such as terbutaline, is that the drug-induced tachycardia may mask maternal compromise.
We are of the opinion that suspected placental abruption contraindicates tocolytic agent use.
Placenta Previa.
# Classification.
The Latin previa means going before, and in this sense, the placenta goes before the fetus into the birth canal.
Placenta previa describes a placenta that is implanted somewhere in the lower uterine segment, either over or very near the internal cervical os.
Because these anatomical relationships cannot always be precisely defined and because they frequently change across pregnancy, terminology can sometimes be confusing.
Terminology for placenta previa has evolved, and the National Institutes of Health (NIH)-sponsored Fetal Imaging Workshop recommends the following classification: • Placenta previa: the internal os is covered partially or completely by placenta (Figs. 43-7 and 43-8).
In the past, these were further classified as either total or partial previa.
Figure 43-7.
Placenta previa showing that copious hemorrhage could be anticipated with any cervical dilation.
Figure 43-8.
On speculum examination, placenta is visible protruding through the cervical os.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Maureen E. Flowers.) • Low-lying placenta: implantation in the lower uterine segment is such that the placental edge does not cover the internal os but lies within a 2-cm wide perimeter around the os.
A previously used term, marginal previa, described a placenta that was at the edge of the internal os but did not overlie it.
Clearly, the classification of some cases will depend on cervical dilation at the time of assessment.
For example, a low-lying placenta at 2-cm dilation may become a partial placenta previa at 4-cm dilation because the cervix has opened to expose the placental edge.
Conversely, a placenta previa that appears to be total before cervical dilation may become partial at 4-cm dilation because the cervical opening now extends beyond the edge of the placenta.
Digital palpation in an attempt to ascertain these changing relations between the placental edge and internal os as the cervix dilates
usually causes severe hemorrhage!
With any degree of placenta previa, a certain amount of spontaneous placental separation is inevitable during lower uterine segment remodeling and cervical dilation.
Although this frequently causes bleeding and thus technically constitutes a placental abruption, this term is usually not applied in these instances.
Somewhat but not always related is vasa previa, in which fetal vessels course through membranes and present at the cervical os.
Vasa previa has been reviewed by the Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2015) and is discussed in Chapter 6 (p. 115).
# Placental Migration.
Beginning with the use of sonography in obstetrics, the term placental migration was coined to describe the apparent movement of the placenta away from the internal os .
Obviously, the placenta does not actually move, and the mechanism of apparent movement is not completely understood.
To begin with, migration is clearly a misnomer, because decidual invasion anchors chorionic villi.
Explanations of placental migration are likely additive.
First, apparent movement of the low-lying placenta relative to the internal os is related to the imprecision of two-dimensional sonography.
Second, as pregnancy progresses, growth of the lower and upper uterine segments differs.
With greater blood flow in the upper uterus, placental growth toward this supply, termed trophotropism, is thus more likely directed toward the fundus.
Many of those placentas that “migrate” most likely never were circumferentially implanted with true villous invasion that reached the internal cervical os.
Importantly, a low-lying placenta or placenta previa is less likely to “migrate” if there is a prior cesarean delivery scar.
The frequency of placental migration has been quantified.
In one study of 4300 women at midpregnancy, 12 percent had a low-lying placenta .
Of placentas not covering the internal os, previa did not persist, and none subsequently had placental hemorrhage.
Conversely, approximately 40 percent of placentas that covered the os at midpregnancy continued to do so until delivery.
Thus, placentas that lie close to but not over the internal os until the early third trimester are unlikely to persist as a previa by term (Heller, 2014; Parrott, 2015).
The chance that placenta previa persists increases with a hysterotomy scar (Kohari, 2012; Oyelese, 2006).
# Incidence and Associated Factors.
The incidence of placenta previa has risen during the past 30 years.
Reported incidences average about 0.4 percent or 1 case per 250 to 400 deliveries .
The frequency at Parkland Hospital from 1988 through 2003 for nearly 250,000 births was 2.6 cases per 1000.
For the 2004 to 2020 epoch, it rose to 3.8 cases per 1000.
Similar frequencies have been reported from Austria, Finland, and Israel (Kollmann, 2016; Räisänen, 2014; Rosenberg, 2011).
Several demographic factors may contribute to this higher rate of placenta previa.
First, maternal age increases the frequency (Biro, 2012; Roberts, 2012).
In the First- and Second-Trimester Evaluation of Risk (FASTER) trial, which included more than 36,000 women, the frequency of previa was 0.5 percent for women <35 years compared with 1.1 percent in those ≥35 years .
At Parkland Hospital, the incidence ranged from a rate of approximately 0.65 cases per 1000 births for women ≤19 years to almost 10 cases per 1000 births for women older than 35.
Multiparity also elevates the rate of placenta previa (Räisänen, 2014).
Obviously, the effects of advancing maternal age and parity are confounding.
Still, Babinszki and colleagues (1999) reported that the 2.2-percent incidence in women with parity of five or greater was significantly higher than that of women with lower parity.
The interpregnancy interval does not affect this rate .
Cigarette smoking increases the relative risk of placenta previa at least twofold .
It has been postulated that carbon monoxide hypoxemia causes compensatory placental hypertrophy and greater surface area.
Smoking may also be related to decidual vasculopathy.
Several clinical
characteristics also raise placenta previa risks.
Foremost, women with one or more prior cesarean deliveries are at greater risk for subsequent placental disorders that include placenta previa, placental abruption, or placenta accreta spectrum (PAS) (Gibbins, 2018; Klar, 2014).
The cumulative risks for placenta previa that accrue with the increasing number of cesarean deliveries are extraordinary.
In one MFMU Network study of 30,132 women undergoing cesarean delivery, the incidence was 1.3 percent for those with only one prior cesarean delivery, but it was 3.4 percent if there were six or more prior cesareans .
In a retrospective cohort of nearly 400,000 women who were delivered of two consecutive singletons, those with a cesarean delivery for the first pregnancy had a 1.6-fold greater rate for previa in the second pregnancy .
These same investigators reported a 1.5-fold higher rate from six similar population-based studies.
This risk is increased eightfold in women with parity greater than four and who have more than four prior cesarean deliveries .
Importantly, women with a prior uterine incision and placenta previa have an increased likelihood that cesarean hysterectomy will be necessary because of associated PAS (p. 761).
In one study, 6 percent of women with a primary cesarean delivery for placenta previa required a hysterectomy.
This rate was 25 percent for women with a placenta previa undergoing repeat cesarean delivery .
Multifetal gestation raises placenta previa risk (Ananth, 2003a; Luke, 2017a).
Compared with monochorionic twins, dichorionic ones show higher rates, which perhaps stems from having two implantation sites .
MSAFP levels, if abnormally elevated for otherwise unexplained reasons during prenatal screening, raise the risk for placenta previa and a host of other abnormalities.
Moreover, women with a placenta previa and comorbid MSAFP level >2.0 multiples of the median (MoM) at 16 weeks’ gestation were at greater risk for late-pregnancy bleeding and preterm birth .
Assisted reproductive technology (ART) used for conception elevates placenta previa rates.
Some of this association may derive from overlapping effects.
First, older women constitute a significant portion of patients electing ART .
Second, even adjusting for multifetal gestation, ART is still associated with higher previa rates .
Last, in one systematic review including nearly 256,000 births, uterine leiomyomas were associated with higher placenta previa rates .
# Clinical Features.
Painless bleeding is the most characteristic event with placenta previa.
Bleeding usually does not develop until near the end of the second trimester or later, but it can begin even before midpregnancy.
Undoubtedly, some late abortions are caused by an abnormally located placenta.
Initial bleeding from a previa usually begins without warning, and this sentinel bleed is rarely so profuse as to prove fatal.
Usually it ceases, only to recur.
However, in perhaps 10 percent of women, particularly those with a placenta implanted near but not over the cervical os, bleeding is delayed until labor onset.
Bleeding at this time varies in degree, and it may mimic placental abruption.
In cases in which the placenta is located over the internal os, a specific sequence of events leads to bleeding.
First, the uterine body remodels to form the lower uterine segment.
With this, the internal os dilates, and some of the implanted placenta inevitably separates.
Bleeding that ensues is augmented by the inherent inability of myometrial fibers in the lower uterine segment to contract and thereby constrict torn vessels.
Similarly, bleeding from this lower-segment implantation site also frequently continues after placental delivery.
Last, lacerations in the friable cervix and lower segment will bleed.
These may be especially problematic following manual removal of a somewhat adhered placenta.
Cervical length may alter the clinical course.
Stafford (2010) but not Trudell (2013), both with their associates, found that a placenta previa and a third-trimester cervical length <30 mm
increased the risks for hemorrhage, uterine activity, and preterm birth.
Similarly, Friszer (2013) but not Trudell (2013), both with their coworkers, showed that women admitted for bleeding had a greater chance of delivery in the subsequent 7 days when the cervical length measured <25 mm sonographically.
Placenta accreta spectrum is a frequent and serious complication associated with placenta previa.
This abnormal placental attachment derives in part from poorly developed decidua that lines the lower uterine segment.
Biswas and coworkers (1999) performed placental bed biopsies in 50 women with a placenta previa and in 50 control women.
Infiltration of spiral arterioles by trophoblastic giant cells, rather than by the expected endovascular trophoblast cells, was found in half of specimens.
In contrast, only 20 percent of biopsies from normally implanted placentas had these changes.
In another study of 514 cases of placenta previa, abnormal placental attachment was identified in 7 percent .
As discussed, placenta previa overlying a prior cesarean incision conveys a particularly high risk for PAS.
Coagulopathy rarely complicate placenta previa, even when implantation site separation is extensive .
Placental thromboplastin, which incites the intravascular coagulation seen with placental abruption, is presumed to readily escape through the cervical canal rather than be forced into the maternal circulation.
The paucity of large myometrial veins in this area also may be protective.
# Diagnosis.
For uterine bleeding after midpregnancy, placenta previa and placental abruption are always considered.
In one Canadian study, placenta previa accounted for 21 percent of women admitted from 22 to 28 weeks’ gestation with vaginal bleeding .
Previa should not be excluded until sonographic evaluation has clearly proved its absence.
If sonography is not readily available, diagnosis by digital cervical examination is done in an operating room and with preparations in place for operative delivery.
We call these preparations a double set-up technique.
Even the gentlest examination can cause torrential hemorrhage.
Using standard sonographic techniques, quick and accurate placental localization can be accomplished .
This is usually done with transabdominal sonography.
If the placenta clearly overlies the cervix or if it lies away from the lower uterine segment, the examination has excellent sensitivity and negative predictive value (Olive, 2006; Quant, 2014).
Obese women may hinder clear viewing of the lower uterine segment.
A full bladder may artificially elongate the cervix and compress the lower uterine segment to give the impression that the placenta overlies the cervix.
If placental location remains unclear, transvaginal sonography is the most accurate sonographic method and is safe even with vaginal bleeding .
In a comprehensive study, the internal os was visualized in all cases with transvaginal sonography but in only 30 percent with transabdominal sonography .
As discussed, if the placental edge lies <2 cm from the internal os, but not covering it, the placenta is considered low lying .
In the absence of any other indication, sonography need not be frequently repeated simply to document placental position.
At Parkland Hospital, women with placenta previa identified at 18 to 22 weeks’ gestation and a prior cesarean delivery are reevaluated sonographically at 28 weeks and again at 32 weeks if it persists.
Those with a placenta previa but without prior cesarean delivery undergo reimaging at 32 weeks.
Restriction of activity is not necessary unless a previa persists beyond 28 weeks’ gestation or if clinical findings such as bleeding or contractions develop before this time.
At 32 weeks’ gestation, if the placental edge is still <2 cm from the os, transvaginal sonography is repeated at 36 weeks’ gestation.
Figure 43-9.
In this transvaginal image at 21 weeks’ gestation, the posterior placenta (P) completely covers the internal cervical os (arrowhead).
The dotted line represents the cervical canal.
Using MR imaging,
several investigators report excellent visualization of placental abnormalities.
However, it is unlikely that this modality will replace sonography for routine evaluation anytime soon given availability and cost differences compared with sonography.
However, MR imaging is useful for evaluation of PAS (p. 761).
# Management.
Care with placenta previa is individualized, and three prominent factors include fetal maturity, associated labor, and bleeding severity.
In one study of 214 women with a placenta previa, 43 percent had an emergency delivery, and half of these were preterm .
Instead, if active bleeding subsides and the fetus is immature, close observation in an obstetrical unit is indicated.
Data are sparse regarding tocolytic administration for uterine contractions.
Although robust randomized trials are lacking, Bose and colleagues (2011) recommend that if tocolytics are given, they be limited to 48 hours of administration.
As noted earlier, the physiological cardiovascular responses to tocolytic agents that include hypotension and tachycardia can mask maternal compromise.
We categorically recommend against their use in this setting.
After bleeding has ceased for approximately 2 days and the fetus is judged to be healthy, a woman can usually be discharged home with instructions for “pelvic rest.
The Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2018) does not recommend routine cervical length screening in these women.
Importantly, the woman and her family must appreciate the possibility of recurrent bleeding and be prepared for immediate transport back to the hospital.
In other cases, prolonged hospitalization may be necessary.
The frequency of emergency delivery in women with placenta previa ranges from 25 to 40 percent (Erfani, 2019; Gibbons, 2018).
In properly selected patients, however, long-term inpatient care does not appear to add benefits compared with outpatient management .
In one randomized study of 53 women who had a bleeding previa at 24 to 36 weeks’ gestation, maternal or fetal morbidity rates did not differ between management methods .
Of all study women, 60 percent had recurrent bleeding, and half eventually required expeditious cesarean delivery.
For women who are near term and who are not bleeding, plans are made for scheduled cesarean delivery.
A planned delivery in a controlled setting is optimal, and timing balances fetal immaturity against antepartum hemorrhage.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2021) recommend delivery for otherwise uncomplicated placenta previa between 360/7 and 376/7 weeks.
At Parkland Hospital, we usually perform elective cesarean delivery at 380/7 weeks.
Recommendations for delivery of women with PAS are outlined in that section.
# Delivery.
Practically all women with placenta previa undergo cesarean delivery.
Some recommend a vertical laparotomy incision to provide rapid entry if bleeding is torrential or if generous operating space is required for hysterectomy.
As discussed, cesarean delivery is emergently performed in more than half because of hemorrhage, for which about a fourth require blood transfusion .
Although a low transverse hysterotomy is usually possible, this may cause fetal bleeding if the placenta is implanted anteriorly and the placenta is incised.
In such cases, fetal delivery should be expeditious .
Thus, a vertical uterine incision may be preferable in some instances.
In either case, even when the incision extends through the placenta, maternal or fetal outcomes are rarely compromised.
Following placental removal, the implantation site may bleed uncontrollably due to poorly contracted smooth muscle, which is characteristic of the lower uterine segment.
If hemostasis at the placental implantation site cannot be obtained by uterotonic agent administration and pressure, it can be oversewn with no. 0 chromic sutures.
Cho and associates (1991) described placing interrupted sutures at 1-cm intervals to form a circle around the bleeding portion of the lower segment to control hemorrhage.
Others
have reported success with compression sutures that traverse and compress the anterior and posterior uterine wall (Mohamed, 2019; Sallam, 2019).
Of other methods, Bakri or Foley balloon tamponade used alone or coupled with compression sutures has been described (Albayrak, 2011; Diemert, 2012).
Other surgical options are bilateral uterine or internal iliac artery ligation, illustrated in Chapter 44 (p. 779).
Pelvic artery embolization also has gained acceptance.
Yu and colleagues (2020) performed a randomized trial of perioperative prophylactic internal iliac artery balloon occlusion during cesarean delivery for placenta previa and found that deployment did not reduce postpartum hemorrhage or alter maternal or neonatal morbidity. If these more conservative methods fail and bleeding is brisk, hysterectomy is necessary.
Placenta previa—especially with PAS—currently is a common indication for peripartum hysterectomy at Parkland Hospital and other institutions (Jakobsson, 2015; Wong, 2011).
In cases without PAS, the reported incidence of hysterectomy with placenta previa is 2 percent .
Thus, it is not possible to accurately estimate the effect on the hysterectomy rate from placenta previa alone without considering the associated PAS.
Again, for women whose placenta previa is implanted anteriorly at the site of a prior uterine incision, the likelihood of an associated morbidly adherent placenta and need for hysterectomy is increased.
In a study of 318 peripartum hysterectomies performed in the United Kingdom, 40 percent were done for abnormal placentation .
At Parkland Hospital, 44 percent of cesarean hysterectomies were done for bleeding placenta previa or for PAS .
The technique for peripartum hysterectomy is described in Chapter 30 (p. 560).
# Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes.
Placenta previa and coexistent PAS both contribute substantively to maternal morbidity and mortality rates.
The maternal mortality ratio is increased approximately threefold for women with a placenta previa .
In a report of 5367 maternal deaths in the United States from 2006 to 2013, placenta previa alone accounted for nearly 3 percent of deaths from hemorrhage (Creanga, 2014, 2017).
The report from the Consortium on Safe Labor emphasizes the ongoing perinatal morbidity with placenta previa .
In these cases, preterm delivery continues to be a major cause of perinatal death (Balachandar, 2020; Nørgaard, 2012; Salihu, 2003).
Ananth and colleagues (2003b) reported a comparably elevated risk of neonatal death even for fetuses who delivered at term.
This is at least partially related to the fetal anomaly rate, which is two- to threefold higher in pregnancies with placenta previa (Crane, 1999; Kancherla, 2015).
The association of fetal-growth restriction with placenta previa is likely minimal after controlling for gestational age.
In a population-based cohort of more than 500,000 singleton births, most low-birthweight newborns associated with placenta previa resulted from preterm birth .
From their large metaanalysis, Balayla and coworkers (2019) found a slightly increased frequency of fetal-growth restriction.
At least two other studies reported an elevated risk (Räisänen, 2014; Weiner, 2016).
Apparently, fetal growth effects are similar with placenta previa and PAS .
Placenta Accreta Spectrum.
The term placenta accreta spectrum (PAS) describes aberrant placentation characterized by abnormally implanted, invasive, or adhered placenta.
Derivation of accreta comes from the Latin ac- + crescere—to adhere or become attached to .
It is also referred to as the morbidly adherent placenta, and in Europe it is referred to as a pernicious placenta previa with accreta and abnormally adherent placenta.
# Etiopathogenesis.
The major clinical problem is placental failure to separate normally from the myometrium after fetal delivery.
This abnormal adherence stems in part from partial or total absence of the decidua basalis and imperfect development of the fibrinoid or Nitabuch layer, described in Chapter 5 (p. 85).
If the decidual spongy layer is lacking either
partially or totally, the physiological line of cleavage is absent, and some or all cotyledons are densely anchored.
Microscopically, placental villi attach to smooth muscle fibers rather than to decidual cells.
This decidual deficiency then prevents normal separation after delivery.
The surface area involved at the implantation site and the depth of trophoblast ingrowth vary between women, but all affected placentas can potentially cause significant hemorrhage.
Data now suggest that PAS is not solely caused by the decidua’s anatomical deficiency.
Indeed, the cytotrophoblasts may control decidual invasion through factors such as angiogenesis (Duzyj, 2018; Goh, 2016).
Moreover, some tissue specimens show immunologically mediated “hyperinvasiveness” .
Some genes that code for remodeling and for adherence may be highly expressed (Matsukawa, 2019; Shainker, 2020).
Myometrial fibers attached to the basal plate in an antecedent pregnancy are predictive markers for a subsequent PAS (Linn, 2015; Miller, 2016).
This implies an antecedent “constitutional endometrial defect” in most cases.
The greater risk conveyed by previous surgical uterine trauma may be partially explained by an enhanced vulnerability to trophoblast invasion (Einerson, 2020; Jauniaux, 2018).
This association with prior trauma is reinforced by the close relationship between cesarean scar pregnancy (CSP) and later development of PAS in the same pregnancy.
Indeed, accruing evidence suggests that CSP and PAS lie on a spectrum and that CSP is a precursor (Happe, 2020; Timor-Tritsch, 2019).
Described in Chapter 12 (p. 229), early rupture and hemorrhage with CSP are not uncommon, and women often elect pregnancy-terminating interventions to avoid these (Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine, 2020; Timor-Tritsch, 2019).
# Classification.
Variants of PAS are classified by the depth of trophoblastic growth (Figs. 4310 and 43-11).
Placenta accreta indicates that villi are attached to the myometrium.
With placenta increta, villi actually invade the myometrium, and placenta percreta defines villi that penetrate through the myometrium and to or through the serosa .
In clinical practice, these three variants are encountered in an approximate ratio of 80:15:5, respectively .
At a referral center, however, the distribution was 22, 24, and 54 percent respectively .
In all three varieties, abnormal adherence may involve all lobules—total placenta accreta.
If all or part of a single lobule is abnormally attached, it is described as focal placenta accreta.
Histological diagnosis cannot be made from the placenta alone, and myometrial samples are necessary for confirmation .
Terminology for consistent classification has been lacking because of varying clinical criteria and lack of detailed pathological examinations.
To alleviate this, the International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) has recently proposed a clinical classification system for PAS .
Figure 43-10.
Placenta accreta spectrum.
A. Placenta accreta.
B. Placenta increta.
C. Placenta percreta.
Figure 43-11.
Varying degrees of myometrial invasion with placenta accreta spectrum disorders.
Incisions begin on the serosal surface and extend through to the placenta.
A. In this case, the myometrium (M) shows minimal invasion by the placenta (P).
S = uterine serosa.
B. A greater degree of myometrial invasion is seen here.
C. In this example, the placenta (brackets) extends to the serosal edge, held by the surgeon’s hand.
No myometrium remains at this site.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. C. Edward Wells in Cunningham FG: Placenta previa and morbidly adherent placenta.
In Yeomans ER, Hoffman BL, Gilstrap LC III, et al (eds): Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd edition.
New York, McGraw Hill Education, 2017.
# Incidence and Risk Factors.
Decades ago, the frequency of PAS was 1 in 20,000 births .
As late as 1971, Hellman and Pritchard in the 14th edition of Williams Obstetrics described PAS as the subject of case reports.
Since then, the incidence has grown remarkably in direct
relationship to the rising cesarean delivery rate.
For example, the incidence was 1 case in 2500 births in the 1980s, but it was 1 case per 731 births in a report from the MFMU Network comprising 115,502 women .
From the Nationwide Inpatient Sample, the PAS rate was an astounding 1 case in 270 births .
This rising frequency has made PAS one of the most formidable problems in obstetrics.
Of 5367 pregnancy-related maternal deaths in the United States from 2006 to 2013, 13 percent were due to hemorrhage caused by PAS (Creanga, 2015, 2017).
In addition, PAS is a leading cause of hemorrhage and emergency peripartum hysterectomy (Awan, 2011; Eller, 2011; Rossi, 2010).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2018) have outlined optimal management.
The International Society for Abnormally Invasive Placenta also has published guidelines .
In subsequent pregnancies following PAS, recurrence risks are high.
Women in whom hysterectomy is avoided have an estimated 20-percent incidence of recurrence (Cunningham, 2016; Roeca, 2017).
Some evidence shows that these women also have greater risks for placenta previa, uterine rupture, manual placental removal, preterm delivery, and hysterectomy (Baldwin, 2020; Eshkoli, 2013).
PAS risk factors are similar to those for placenta previa (p. 756).
Shown in Figure 43-12, the two most important elements are an associated placenta previa, a prior cesarean delivery, or more likely both (Klar, 2014; Silver, 2006).
A classical hysterotomy incision has a higher risk for subsequent PAS than a lower uterine segment one .
Of women with a prior cesarean delivery, almost half had myometrial fibers seen microscopically adhered to the placenta (Hardardottir, 1996; Miller, 2016).
Dysfunctional decidua may also follow other myometrial trauma such as curettage or endometrial ablation (Baldwin, 2018; Gill, 2015).
ART is an independent risk factor for PAS .
Figure 43-12.
Frequency of placenta accreta spectrum in women with one to four prior cesarean deliveries (CDs) and now with a placenta previa.
Other risk markers are prenatal MSAFP and human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) used to screen for neural-tube defects and aneuploidies.
In one study of more than 9300 women screened at 14 to 22 weeks’ gestation, the risk for PAS was eightfold higher with MSAFP levels >2.5 MoM, and it was increased fourfold with maternal serum free β-hCG levels >2.5 MoM .
# Diagnosis.
With first- and second-trimester PAS, hemorrhage usually stems from a coexisting placenta previa.
Such bleeding will typically prompt evaluation, and ideally sonography is used (Chantraine, 2013; Jauniaux, 2018).
With lesser degrees of bleeding, first-trimester measurement of the smallest myometrial thickness can help predict the later risk for peripartum hysterectomy with PAS .
In a screening study of more than 22,000 singleton pregnancies at 11 to 13 weeks’ gestation, 6 percent were at high risk for PAS .
However imaging was less than perfect to identify all of these placentas early.
Subsequently, only 14 had a suspected clinical diagnosis, and 13 of these were confirmed at delivery.
Five characteristic sonographic findings suggest PAS: (1) placental lacunae; (2) thinning of the retroplacental myometrium; (3) disruption of the bladder-uterine serosal interface; (4) bridging vessels from the placenta to the bladder-serosal interface; and (5) placental bulge that pushes outward and distorts the contour of the uterus .
In a metaanalysis, the sensitivities of these criteria to identify placenta accreta, increta, and percreta were 91, 93, and 89 percent, respectively.
Corresponding specificities were 97, 98, and 99 percent, respectively .
Figure 43-13.
Transabdominal sonogram of placental percreta shows multiple and massive placental “lakes” or “lacunae” (L).
These figures may be overestimated because of clinical bias and considerable interobserver variability .
Some investigators report fewer spectacular results with sonography (Jauniaux, 2016; Primo, 2014).
Bowman and colleagues
2014) described the sensitivity of sonography to be 54 percent; specificity, 88 percent; positive predictive value, 82 percent; negative predictive value, 65 percent; and accuracy, 65 percent.
Location affects sonographic accuracy.
Posterior placental location is associated with delayed diagnosis and increased surgical complications (Morgan, 2019; Tinari, 2021).
In one study, the detection rate was 90 percent for anterior placenta accreta compared with 50 percent for posterior ones .
Nageotte (2014) concluded that identification of PAS with sonography should be interpreted with clinical and operative findings.
Better results have been found by some using three-dimensional (3-D) sonography and power Doppler .
We too have found that the addition of Doppler color flow mapping aids prediction of myometrial invasion .
Invasion is suspected if the distance between the uterine serosa–bladder wall interface and the retroplacental vessels measures <1 mm and if large intraplacental lacunae are seen (Rac, 2015a; Twickler, 2000).
In another study, hypervascularity of the uterine serosa– bladder wall interface had the highest positive and negative predictive values for placenta percreta .
Intracervical lakes also have been reported with placenta percreta (di Pasquo, 2020).
Figure 43-14.
Transvaginal sonogram of placental invasion with a placenta percreta.
Retroplacental vessels (color Doppler) invade the myometrium, and abnormal intraplacental venous lakes (L) are commonly seen in this setting.
Yule and coworkers (2020) reported that the placenta accreta index was useful for diagnosis.
This index incorporates the number of prior cesarean deliveries, placental location, lacunae, bridging vessels, and smallest myometrial distance.
These investigators are also exploring first-trimester color mapping to develop a quantification algorithm .
To further delineate anatomy, MR imaging can be added.
We and others use it to identify invasion of adjacent structures (Chalubinski, 2013; Reddy, 2014).
Interobserver variability was reported to be excellent to diagnose PAS and assess invasion depth.
There was less agreement in assessing topography of invasion .
Using MR imaging, Mori and colleagues (2020) described a high prevalence of pelvic parasitic arteries with PAS.
However, not all investigators have found MR imaging to be beneficial .
Although gadolinium is usually not added during pregnancy, this contrast may enhance images .
Lax and coworkers (2007) described three MR imaging findings that suggest PAS: uterine bulging, dark intraplacental bands on T2-weighted imaging, and heterogeneous signal intensity within the placenta indicative of lacunae.
Some recommend MR imaging if sonography results are inconclusive or there is a posterior previa (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2018; Silver, 2018).
# Management.
Preoperative assessment ideally begins once a possible PAS is recognized antenatally.
A major decision concerns the timing and the ideal facility for delivery.
Considerations include appropriate surgical, anesthesia, intensive care, and blood banking capabilities.
An obstetrical surgeon or gynecological oncologist and surgical, urological, and interventional radiological consultants should be available (Collins, 2019; Shamshirsaz, 2018).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018) and the Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine recommend planned delivery in a tertiary-care facility.
In some, specially designed teams have been assembled and are on call .
A metaanalysis described the improved maternal outcomes with such management .
Silver and colleagues (2015b) have provided requisites for accreta centers of excellence and their criteria to consider transfer to a higher levelof-care hospital .
If possible, delivery is best scheduled for peak availability of all resources and team members.
Even so, a third of cases require unscheduled delivery, and contingency plans should be ready .
Women who refuse blood or its derivatives pose especially difficult management dilemmas .
Table 43-2.
Criteria to
Consider for Delivery of Placenta Accreta Spectrum (PAS) in a Center of Excellence Delivery Timing In one study, 40 percent of women with PAS had bleeding mandating unplanned delivery prior to 34 weeks’ gestation.
Timing balances fetal immaturity against adverse maternal consequences of hemorrhage and emergency cesarean delivery (Perlman, 2017; Pettit, 2019).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018; 2021) recommends individualization and suggests delivery between 340/7 and 356/7 weeks’ gestation.
They cite a decision-analysis study that justifies elective delivery without fetal lung maturity testing after 34 completed weeks .
The Society for Maternal–Fetal Medicine (2018) recommends delivery between 34 and 37 weeks.
Two earlier surveys found that most practitioners do not deliver these women until 36 weeks or later (Esakoff, 2012; Wright, 2013).
At Parkland Hospital, we generally schedule these procedures after 36 completed weeks but are prepared also to manage them in nonelective situations .
In some cases, PAS is not recognized until laparotomy.
If resources are inadequate to surgically manage the percreta and if the woman is stable and not bleeding, the fetus is not delivered.
The abdominal incision is closed, and she is transferred to a tertiary-care facility.
Preoperative Prophylactic Catheterization In cases that may involve the ureters, catheterization may aid their dissection or identification.
However, these catheters overall do not lower urinary tract injury rates .
Some, but not all, advocate preoperative ureteral catheterization (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2018; Eller, 2011).
The role of catheters for ureteral injury repair is outlined in Chapter 30 (p. 564).
With arterial catheterization, balloon-tipped catheters aim to mitigate blood loss and thereby enhance surgical visibility.
Catheters are advanced preoperatively into the internal iliac arteries and are inflated after fetal delivery to occlude pelvic blood flow (Ballas, 2012; Desai, 2012; Zhou, 2021).
Some prefer an infrarenal aortic balloon occlusion catheter .
Alternatively, the catheters can be used to deliver occluding emboli to bleeding arterial sites .
Others have concluded that these procedures offer borderline efficacy and have serious risks (Chen, 2020; Makary, 2019; Mohr-Sasson, 2020).
Rare complications have included thrombosis of the common iliac artery .
At this time, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018) concludes that a firm recommendation cannot be made for or against intraarterial catheter use.
Similarly, there are no obvious benefits to prophylactic internal iliac artery ligation in this setting (Po, 2012; Yu, 2020).
Cesarean Delivery and Hysterectomy Before commencing with delivery, the risk of hysterectomy to prevent exsanguination should be estimated.
Some of these abnormal placentations, especially if partial, may be amenable to placental delivery with hemostatic suture placement.
Confirmation of a percreta or increta almost always mandates hysterectomy.
Because the scope of invasion may not be apparent before delivery of the fetus, some complete a number of dissection steps early.
This also minimizes blood loss during potentially tedious dissection after hysterotomy and if the placenta bleeds.
Thus, an attempt can be made to create a wide bladder flap before making the hysterotomy incision .
The round ligaments are divided, and the lateral edges of the peritoneal reflection are dissected downward.
If possible, these incisions are extended to encircle the entire placental implantation site that visibly occupies the prevesical space and posterior bladder wall.
Following this, a classical hysterotomy, transverse fundal, or high posterior incision is made to avoid the placenta .
After fetal delivery, the extent of placental invasion is assessed without attempts at manual placental removal.
In a report from the United Kingdom, attempts at partial or total placental removal prior to hysterectomy were associated with twice as much blood loss .
Generally
speaking, with obvious percreta or increta, hysterectomy is usually the best course, and the placenta is left in situ.
With more extensive placental ingrowth, bleeding may be minimal until manual placental removal is attempted.
Unless there is spontaneous separation with bleeding that mandates emergency hysterectomy, the operation begins after full assessment is made.
Cesarean hysterectomy is carried out as described in Chapter 30 (p.560).
With heavy bleeding, successful treatment depends on immediate blood replacement and other measures that can include uterine or internal iliac artery ligation, balloon occlusion, or embolization.
In some cases, the operation is made easier by performance of a supracervical hysterectomy .
Kingdom and colleagues (2020) have described a modified radical hysterectomy for PAS .
This technique is also detailed in Cunningham and Gilstrap’s Operative Obstetrics, 3rd edition .
Because of a high risk for postoperative venous thromboembolism, consideration is given for thromboprophylaxis .
Table 43-3.
Steps in Cesarean Hysterectomy for Management of Placenta Percreta Conservative Management Occasionally, it may be possible to trim the umbilical cord, repair the hysterotomy incision, leave the placenta in situ, and not pursue hysterectomy .
This option may be used for women in whom abnormal placentation was not suspected before cesarean delivery and in whom uterine closure stops bleeding.
After this, she can be transferred to a higher level-ofcare facility for definitive management.
Another consideration is the woman with a strong desire for fertility and who has received extensive counseling.
Resection of the adherent placenta and underlying myometrium has been advocated as a uterine-sparing technique .
Conservative management was reviewed by Perez-Delboy (2014) and Fox (2015) and their colleagues.
In some of these cases, the placenta spontaneously resorbed between 1 and 12 months with a mean of 6 months.
Numerous complications can occur and include sepsis, coagulopathy, pulmonary embolism, and arteriovenous malformation (Fox, 2015; Judy, 2015; Roach, 2015).
In other cases, sutures are placed through the outside wall of the uterus overlying the placental bed.
Shih and associates (2019) described this using a Nausicaa procedure.
In some of these women, a subsequent hysterectomy—either planned or prompted by bleeding or infection—is performed days to weeks postpartum when blood loss might be less (Al-Khan, 2014; Sentilhes, 2009, 2021; Zuckerwise, 2020).
In some studies, 20 percent or fewer of women ultimately required hysterectomy (Bretelle, 2007; Kutuk, 2018).
In other reports, however, up to 60 percent eventually required emergency hysterectomy (Clausen, 2013; Pather, 2014).
Evidence that treatment with methotrexate aids resorption is lacking.
Last, for women in whom the placenta is left in situ, serial serum β-hCG measurements are not informative, and serial sonographic or MR imaging is recommended (Timmermans, 2007; Worley, 2008).
At this time, we agree with the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2018) that leaving the placenta in situ should be considered investigational.
Exceptions permit transfer to a higher level of care.
Guidelines from the International Society for Abnormally Invasive Placenta are more permissive .
# Pregnancy Outcomes.
In sum, PAS can have disastrous outcomes for both mother and fetus.
Although the depth of placental invasion does not correspond with perinatal outcome, it is of paramount maternal significance.
Table 43-4 displays outcomes of women at tertiary-care hospitals and in whom the PAS diagnosis was usually made preoperatively.
Despite these advantages, complications included hemorrhage, urinary tract injury, intensive care unit admission, secondary surgical procedures, and maternal death.
Some of these same reports chronicle outcomes in a second cohort of women in whom care was not given at a tertiary-care facility or in whom the diagnosis of percreta was not made until delivery, or both.
In these cohorts, morbidity and mortality rates
were higher .
Table 43-4.
Selected Maternal Outcomes in Women with Placenta Accreta Spectrum Identified Prenatally and Delivered in Tertiary-Care Units